Edward Bliss Papers MS125
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Edward Bliss Papers
1938 -- 1961
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Bliss, Edward
MS125
2.5 Linear Feet
9 Audiovisual Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series: Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files; Bliss Omitted Features by date; and Selections of Edward R. Murrow's "This...is London".
Custodial History
The materials housed in this collection are assumed to have been donated to the Fletcher School by Edward Bliss.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of the papers and audio reels, presumably used by Bliss in editing a volume of Edward R. Murrow's broadcasts, In Search of Light: The Broadcasts of Edward R. Murrow, 1938-1961 (New York: Knopf, 1967). The papers consist of summary descriptions of important events and transcriptions of parts of key speeches, broadcasts, and events that Murrow attended. There are 9 audio reels of "This...Is London" from 1940.
Related Materials
MS025, Edward R. Murrow, papers, DCA.
Biographical / Historical
Edward "Ed" Bliss, Jr. was born on July 30, 1912 to Edward Lydston and May Bortz Bliss in Fuzhou, China, where his father was a missionary. After graduating from college in 1935, he worked as a print journalist and a news editor for several small newspapers in Columbus, Ohio.
In 1943, Bliss was hired by CBS to work the night shift. He was a producer and editor for Edward R. Murrow from 1945 to 1955. Bliss also served as an assistant to the president of CBS News in 1962 before becoming editor of "CBS Evening News with Walter Cronkite" in 1963. Bliss left CBS News in 1968 to establish the broadcast journalism program at the School of Communication at American University in Washington, D.C. He taught at American University until 1977. After retiring as a full professor, Bliss remained active as a news consultant for stations across the United States. Bliss died in Alexandria, Virginia on November 25, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Bliss, Edward, 1912-2002; History, Modern -- 20th century.; Media and broadcast history
- Bliss omitted feature subject files, 1938 -- 1961; MS125.001.001; 2.0 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This subseries consists of Bliss' files, arranged by subject, for "In Search of Light."
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by subject.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, World War II, 1938 -- 1945; MS125.001.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    former folder # 7-C-4
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, A Reporter Remembers, 1938 -- 1946; MS125.001.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    former folder # 7-C-9
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Sunday Broadcasts - 7:45 Think Pieces, 1938 -- 1950; MS125.001.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    former folder # 7-C-30
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, This Is London, 1939 -- 1941; MS125.001.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    former folder # 7-C-8
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Misc. Programs and Speeches, 1941 -- 1961; MS125.001.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
    former folder # 7-C-35
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Miscellaneous, 1943 -- 1958; MS125.001.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    former folder # 7-C-1
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Miscellaneous, 1943 -- 1959; MS125.001.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
    former folder # 7-C-11
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, International-Europe-U.N., 1944 -- 1959; MS125.001.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
    former folder # 7-C-3
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, McCarthyism, 1947 -- 1955; MS125.001.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
    former folder # 7-C-5
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Washington/L.A., 1947 -- 1960; MS125.001.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
    former folder # 7-C-2
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, ERM Broadcast Notes, 1948 -- 1950; MS125.001.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
    former folder # 7-C-13
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Far East, 1950 -- 1958; MS125.001.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
    former folder # 7-C-6
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Miscellaneous Programs, 1951 -- 1960; MS125.001.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
    former folder # 7-C-32
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Miscellaneous Speeches, 1953 -- 1960; MS125.001.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
    former folder # 7-C-36
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Newspaper Clippings (Las Vegas Sun, February 1-6, 1954), MS125.001.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Miscellaneous Programs, 1954 -- 1960; MS125.001.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
    former folder # 7-C-31
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, ERM-Untitled Manuscript, 1957; MS125.001.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
    former folder # 7-C-29
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Small World, 1958 -- 1959; MS125.001.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
    former folder # 7-C-33
  - Bliss Omitted Feature Subject Files, Background, 1960 -- 1961; MS125.001.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
    former folder # 7-C-34
- Bliss omitted features by date, 1938 -- 1961; MS125.001.002; 1.0 Linear Feet
  This subseries consists of Bliss' files, arranged by date, for "In Search of Light."
  This subseries is arranged by date.
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1938 -- 1947; MS125.001.002.004.00004 (Box 4)
    March-September. former folder # 7-C-7
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1946 -- 1952; MS125.001.002.004.00005 (Box 4)
    January-December. former folder # 7-C-10
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1947 -- 1952; MS125.001.002.004.00006 (Box 4)
    October-December. former folder # 7-C-12
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1950; MS125.001.002.004.00007 (Box 4)
    April-December. former folder # 7-C-14
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1950; MS125.001.002.005.00001 (Box 5)
    July-December. former folder # 7-C-15
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1951; MS125.001.002.005.00002 (Box 5)
    January-December. former folder # 7-C-16&17&18
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1952; MS125.001.002.005.00003 (Box 5)
    January-December. former folder # 7-C-19&20
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1953; MS125.001.002.005.00004 (Box 5)
    January-December. former folder # 7-C-21
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1954; MS125.001.002.005.00005 (Box 5)
    January-December. former folder # 7-C-22
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1955; MS125.001.002.005.00006 (Box 5)
    January-December. former folder # 7-C-23&24
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1956; MS125.001.002.005.00007 (Box 5)
    January-December. former folder # 7-C-25
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1957; MS125.001.002.005.00008 (Box 5)
    January-December. former folder # 7-C-26
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1958; MS125.001.002.005.00009 (Box 5)
    January-December. former folder # 7-C-27
  - Bliss Omitted Features by date, 1959 -- 1961; MS125.001.002.005.00010 (Box 5)
    January-January. former folder # 7-C-28
- Selections of Edward R. Murrow's "This...is London", 1940; MS125.002; 9 Audiovisual Object(s)
  This series consists of nine 7" reel audiotape selections from Murrow's "This is...London"
  This series is not arranged.
  - Edward R. Murrow - "This ... is London", Tape 1, Cuts 1-5 (8/11/1940-8/17/1940), MS125.002.006 (Reel 6)
    sound tape reel Tape 1: Cut 1 8/11/40 1419 Cut 2 8/12/40 1422 Cut 3 8/13/40 1423 Cut 4 8/16/40 1429 Cut 5 8/17/40 1430
    sound tape reel
  - Edward R. Murrow - "This ... is London", Tape 2, Cuts 1-6 (8/18/1940-8/25/1940), MS125.002.007 (Reel 7)
    sound tape reel Tape 2: Cut 1 8/18/40 1432 Cut 2 8/19/40 1435 Cut 3 8/20/40 1436 Cut 4 8/22/40 1439 Cut 5 8/24/40 1444 Cut 6 8/25/40 1445
  - Edward R. Murrow - "This ... is London", Tape 3, Cuts 1-6 (8/26/1940-9/5/1940), MS125.002.008 (Reel 8)
    sound tape reel Tape 3: *few seconds missing due to snarled tape Cut 1 8/26/40 1447 NG Cut 2 8/27/40 1448 Good open Cut 3 8/28/40 1450 Good open Cut 4 8/29/40 1452 Good open Cut 5 9/1/40 1456 Davis? Cut 6 9/5/40 1461 ?
  - Edward R. Murrow - "This ... is London", Tape 5, Cuts 1-5 (9/12/1940-9/17/1940), MS125.002.009 (Reel 9)
    sound tape reel Tape 5: Cut 1 9/12/40 1473 Cut 2 9/14/40 1475 Cut 3 9/14/40 1476 Cut 4 9/15/40 1477 Cut 5 9/17/40 1480
  - Edward R. Murrow - "This ... is London", Tape 6, Cuts 1-5 (9/19/1940-9/25/1940), MS125.002.010 (Reel 10)
    sound tape reel Tape 6: Cut 1 9/19/40 1482 Cut 2 9/22/40 1484 Cut 3 9/23/40 1488 Cut 4 9/24/40 1490 Cut 5 9/25/40 1491
  - Edward R. Murrow - "This ... is London", Tape 7, Cuts 1-5 (9/29/1940-10/5/1940), MS125.002.011 (Reel 11)
    sound tape reel Tape 7: Cut 1 9/29/40 1496 Cut 2 9/30/40 1498 Cut 3 10/1/40 1500 Cut 4 10/4/40 1504 Cut 5 10/5/40 1505
  - Edward R. Murrow - "This ... is London", Tape 8, Cuts 1-5 (10/6/1940-10/10/1940), MS125.002.012 (Reel 12)
    sound tape reel Tape 8: Cut 1 10/6/40 1507 Cut 2 10/7/40 1509 Cut 3 10/8/40 1510 Cut 4 10/10/40 1514 Cut 5 10/10/40 1515
  - Edward R. Murrow - "This ... is London", Tape 9, Cuts 1-5 (10/11/1940-10/17/1940), MS125.002.013 (Reel 13)
    sound tape reel Tape 9: Cut 1 10/11/40 1516 Cut 2 10/13/40 1519 Cut 3 10/14/40 1521 Cut 4 10/15/40 1522 Cut 5 10/17/40 1525
  - Edward R. Murrow - "This ... is London", Tape 10, Cuts 1-7 (10/18/1940-10/28/1940), MS125.002.014 (Reel 14)
    sound tape reel Tape 10: Cut 1 10/18/40 1526 Cut 2 10/20/40 1528 Cut 3 10/21/40 1530 Cut 4 10/22/40 1531 Cut 5 10/23/40 1532 Cut 6 10/27/40 1534 Cut 7 10/28/40 1536